Hello everyone My name is Momoko Hayamizu
Welcome to my youtube channel
In this video，I will explain some of my research results in the field of combinatorial phylogenetics
The goal of today’s lecture is to introduce you to the area of discrete mathematical biology
So i start by providing some basics of phylogenetics and discrete mathematics
And then describe some combinatorial problems on phylogenetic trees and networks
Which will be solved in the next lecture
So what is phylogenetics
phylogenetics is the study of relationships among different groups of organisms
and their evolutionary development
It’s concerned with tracing the evolutionary histories of organisms
typically by analyzing their genetic or morphological similarities
The term for phylogenetics may not be quite familiar to you
But i think most of you have probably seen a tree
depicting the evolutionary processes of different species
Such as humans chimpanzees gorillas and so on
As you see
evolutionary relationships between organisms are commonly represented by a tree
called phylogenetic tree
Tree is a fundamental model for describing the evolution of organisms
And have various applications
Including the study of viral evolution
"Interestingly, phylogenetic trees are also widely used in non-biological disciplines"
To perform hierarchical clustering For example
By constructing phylogenetic tree from time series data of stock prices
We can find clusters of similar companies
Indeed trees are very useful because they are easy to compute
Easy to draw and easy to interpret
This is why trees have so many applications
However trees have critical drawbacks
"Obviously, they are too simple or too restrictive to accurately represent complicated information"
This is problematic because real world data are almost never precisely represented by a tree
And when we analyze real-world data
We must deal with noise and uncertainty in them
"To see this, let’s look at two simple examples illustrated here"
Suppose we wish to estimate evolution of three species
Fish dolphins and cats
The first example illustrates the situation
Where the graph reconstructed from the data are not very tree-like
Possibly due to noises or errors in the data
But the correct evolutionary history should be represented by a tree
As indicated by the solid line
As in this example
Even if a tree is an appropriate model
We always need to handle such noise or errors in the data
The next picture illustrates a similar but different situations
Imagine that we have two different sources of information
On the similarities between the species
And that one source is more reliable than the other
Just for illustrative purposes
Suppose we have constructed two evolutionary trees
From morphological data and from genetic data respectively
And the tree reconstructed from the genetic information is thought to be more reliable
We assemble so
According to the genetic data
The evolutionary scenario shown by the blue line is correct with probability 0.9
As we know dolphins are mammals
and are genetically closer to cats than to fish
So by focusing on the genetic data
We obtain this evolutionary tree with likely for 0.9
As indicated by the blue solid line
"By contrast, morphologically dolphins are obviously closer to fish in appearance"
So as indicated by the red solid line
The morphological data suggests that
The other possibility whose likelihood is 0.1
Less likely than the first one but it’s not negligible
This is a case of uncertainty about the true evolutionary history
As the second example shows
A single phylogenetic tree is often not sufficient to fully describe the given information
So we need to use two or more incompatible trees possibly with different weights
In order to accurately represent such complex information
This is not the focus of this lecture
But let me just mention there are other situations
Where phylogenetic trees do not work very well
For example as you see on the left
It’s common for new species to arise from hybridization of different species
Especially in the case of plants
Hybridization is a event that requires merging as well as branching
So we can’t describe that event by a phylogenetic tree
Apart from that
It’s also well known that in the case of bacteria and viruses
A special event called horizontal gene transfer can occur
As you see on the right
In the case of most animals
"Including human genes, are only transmitted vertically from parents to offspring"
As all of us know
We can’t get a good gene from a friend or seven nearby
But surprisingly to us
Some bacteria and viruses have a way to do so
This is called horizontal gene transfer
Which is another example of known tree-like exploration evolution
In this lecture i will not discuss these topics further
But the important thing is
There are many situations in biology that requiure graph structures more complex trees
This is why we consider phylogenetic networks
They are generalization of phylogenetic trees
Phylogenetic networks provide a more flexible model of evolution
Because they allow not only branching
But also merging of evolutionary analogies
But this doesn’t mean that network models are always more useful than trees
It’s true that extending the concept of phylogenetic trees
Phylogenetic networks are able to represent complex data and phenomena
But many problems related to phylogenetic networks have shown to be np hard
And also there are still many computational problems
Whose complexity is not well understood
The focus of this lecture is as we have seen earlier
The situation where we wish to identify the true tree
Inside a complex phylogenetic network
It’s similar to the idea of removing noise from measured raw data to extract meaningful signals
Likewise we use a phylogenetic network to accurately represent real-world data
And then estimate the true evolutionary tree to explain the data by removing unnecessary arcs
there are many of different computational problems relevant to this setting
for example the most basic is the decision and search problems
"informally speaking, given the phylogenetic network"
the decision problem asks whether the underlying tree of the network exists
and the search problem asks to find the underlying tree if it exists
as you see it's possible that there are two or more underlying the trees in the same network
so the counting problem asks how many there are
and the listing problem asks to generate all or a designated number of underlying trees
and the optimization problem asks to find the best one
because so far i have only shown small examples
these computational problems may seem too easy
but look at this picture
if the size of the network increases just a little bit
it's not quite obvious how many solutions there are and which one is optimal
i will state these problems more formally later today
but important thing is the focus of my study is not placed on creating algorithm
for each problem or analyzing the complexity of each problem
rather the key point of my study is the development of a more general framework
for solving different problems in a unified manner
so just like the structure theorem for finitely generated Abelian groups
which i think learned in algebra class
i proved structural theorem for phylogenetic networks
which reveals the uniquely decomposable structure of phytogenetic networks
And the set of underlying trees
as i'll show you in the next lecture
The structural theorem for phylogenetic networks
immediately derives a series of fast algorithms for various computational problems
okay so before formally stating those problems
i'll explain necessary mathematical terms and notation
a graph is defined to be a pair of sets of vertices and edges
and two graphs are called isomorphic if there exists a bijection that preserves adjacency
so informally as illustrated here
Two graphs can be considered to be the same graph even if they look very different
in this lecture i'll use the terms graph and network interchangeably
all graphs considered here are finite
which means that both the number of vertices and the number of arcs are finite and simple
which means no multiple arcs and no loops
and directed which means every edge is oriented
and acyclic which means no directed cycles
the two figures at the bottom are examples of such a graph
as i said a graph is defined to be a pair of sets of vertices and arcs
so a graph having a set of vertices v and a set of arcs a
is denoted by an ordered pair of v and a
also given the graph g
v of g represents the set of vertices of g
and a of g represents the set of arcs of g
this is also a standard graph theoretical notation
and arc oriented from vertex u to a vertex v
is denoted by close parenthesis u v
"for any arc a, the head of arc a means the vertex which a arrives at"
and the tail of a refers to the vertex which a starts from
given a vertex v of a graph g
the number of arcs incoming to v is called in degree of v
similarly the number of arcs outgoing from v is called out degree of v
for example the vertex v in this figure has in degree 1 and out degree 2.
given a graph the operation of subdividing its arc
consists of inserting a new vertex
and replacing the arc in question with the directed path from path of length two
the resulting graph is called a subdivision of original graph
for example so a graph h is a subdivision of a graph g
the reverse operation of arc subdivision is called vertex smoothing
and two graphs are said to be homeomorphic
if they are isomorphic after smoothing all vertices of in degree 1 and out degree 1.
for example graph g and graph h are not isomorphic
but they are homeomorphic
the composition of a graph is one of the key words in this lecture
suppose g is a graph and a prime is a subset of its arc set
"for example for a graph g depicted in the bottom,a1 is a subset of its arc set right"
"so if we choose a1, then the two arcs in a1 specify the graph in red"
g parenthesis a1 close parenthesis
which is the sub graph of g induced by a1
next we consider partitioning the arc set a of g into non-empty subsets
here we have partitioned a of g into three subsets a1 a2 and a3
then each subset induces a sub graph of graph g as indicated different colors
the collection of these three are called the composition of a graph g
"in this lecture, the symbol x always denotes a non-empty finite set"
which can be interpreted as a set of present-day species
the set x is sometimes called label set or leave set
so we now state the definitions of phylogenetic trees and networks
here i define phylogenetic networks first
Because phylogenetic trees are just a special case of them
"so a phylogenetic network, more formally a rooted binary phylogenetic x-network"
or a phylogenetic network on x
is defined to be any directed and acyclic graph n
that has the following three properties
first there exists a one to one correspondence between the labels at x and the set of leaves of n
and second n has a unique route whose in degree is zero
third any other vertex has in degree one out degree two or in degree 2 and out degree 1.
a vertex of in degree 2 and out degree 1 is called reticulation vertex of n
in the case when n has no reticulation vertex
and is particularly called a rooted binary phylogenetic x tree or tree on x
in this lecture we often omit rooted binary and stuff
because we only consider such networks
for notational simplicity we use the notation tx and nx
to represent collections of all rooted binary phylogenetic x trees and networks
okay so we have defined phylogenetic trees and its generalization phylogenetic networks
there are many subclasses of phylogenetic networks
but in this lecture we discuss problems regarding tree-based networks
as shown here so are tree-based networks
as the name indicates
tree-based networks are phylogenetic networks that can be obtained from a phylogenetic tree
well they are very easy to construct
we first pick any rooted binary phytogenetic x tree as a base initial tree
then if we subdivide arcs of the base tree
then new vertices appear
like this they are new vertices
then we place extra arcs between them
and perform the vertical smoothing operation where possible
the resulting phylogenetic network is called tree-based network
so they can be intuitively understood as a phylogenetic tree plus additional noises
this definition is fine
but in this lecture i use another as following equivalent definition
suppose n is a rooted binary phylogenetic x network
and t prime is a rooted binary phylogenetic x network
the same x
then if has a spanning tree t that is a subdivision of t prime
then n is called a tree-based network and t is called subdivision tree of n
remember in the previous example about the evolution of fish dolphins and cats
we can see that a subdivision tree of n
is nothing but a tree underlying the non-tree-like data
here are some important remarks on tree-based networks and subdivision trees
first tree-base networks form a proper subclass of phylogenetic networks
In other words
there exists a phylogenetic network that has no subdivision tree
the network on the right is an example of such a network
from this observation it's natural to ask
given a phylogenetic network n
how to determine whether n is tree based or not
and how to find subdivision tree of n if n is tree-based
this is what decision and search problems are asking for
the second remark is that
Any phylogenetic network can be converted into tree based network
by attaching extra leaves
this observation leads to the following variant of the decision problem which i call
the deviation quantification problem
the question here is
how to measure deviation from being tree-based
The deviation measure delta
is defined to be the minimum number of extra leaves required to make entryways
this problem is a variant of the previous decision problem
in the decision problem
the only question is whether the network is tree based or not
so the answer is always yes or no
but in this problem
if the network is not tree-based
"we want to evaluate, we want to quantify"
how much the network deviates from being tree based
the final remark is that
as i said tree based network can have many subdivision trees
this example network has only two
but in general the number of subdivision trees can be exponentially many
so it's natural to ask how to compute the number alpha
this is what the counting problem is asking for
likewise a listing problem requires computing a list of all subdivision trees of n
so far we have only considered problems
where the input network is unweighted
but as i mentioned at the beginning
it's also interesting to consider optimization problems
Where each arc has a positive weight
such as a probability
and we want to maximize some objective functions such as the likelihood or log likelihood
there was no previous work on this optimization problem
but recalling alpha can be exponential
we can immediately see that a naive approach would take exponential time
the last problem is a combination of the optimization problem
"and the enumeration problem, a listing problem"
in many practical situations the value of the objective function can be almost the same in the first second third and kth places
in such situations
it's not a good idea to compute only one optimal tree
ignoring all the nearly optimal solutions
that might be very meaningful or insightful biologically
so it's meaningful to consider how to
compute the ranking of top k trees in a tree based networks
to recap today's lecture
we have learned the definitions of phylogenetic trees and networks
and the concepts of tree based networks and subdivision trees
then we have seen various computational problems
associated with finding the true evolutionary tree within complicated phylogenetic network
okay this is the end of today's lecture
in the next video i'll show you a structure theorem for phylogenetic networks
that solves all the problems we discussed today